A Guide to the Virginia Tech LGBTQ Oral History Collection, 2014-2015
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
- Oral History with Edward Spencer, November 7, 2014, 2014-11-07, Ms2015-007_VTLGBTQ_SpencerEdward; 00:42:28
  In his interview, Spencer discusses his career in university administration, his work with LGBTQ student organizations and how attitudes and treatment of the LGBTQ community on campus has changed since the 1980s. The interview was conducted at Edward Spencer’s Residence, Blacksburg, VA. David Atkins was the interviewer and Ellen Boggs was the technical assistant.
  Oral History with Edward Spencer, November 7, 2014.
  Sexual minorities; University History; Local/Regional History and Appalachian South; Atkins, David; Spencer, Edward; Spencer, Edward
- Oral History with Michael Sutphin, November 5, 2014, 2014-11-05, Ms2015-007_VTLGBTQ_SutphinMichael; 00:43:20
  Michael Sutphin was a student at Virginia Tech from 2002-2006. While at Tech, he was a student activist involved with LGBTA (now HokiePRIDE) and a writer and editor for the Collegiate Times. During his time on campus he organized the first Freedom to Marry demonstration on the Drillfield in 2004 and served as the President of the LGBTA in 2005. After graduation, he worked for the College of Agriculture and Life Science, which lead him to his current position as the public relations coordinator for the Virginia-Maryland Regional College of Veterinary Medicine. Since 2011, Sutphin has also served on the Town Council for the City of Blacksburg, and he's currently vice-chair of Equality Virginia, the state's largest LGBTQ group.
  In this interview, Sutphin discusses his involvement on campus and on the Town Council, his activism in the LGBTQ community, and the current climate towards the LGBTQ community and the community's future. The interview was conducted at Michael Sutphin’s residence in Blacksburg, VA. Molly Lash was the interviewer and Amanda Lilly was the technical assistant.
  Oral History with Michael Sutphin, November 5, 2014.
  Sexual minorities; University History; Local/Regional History and Appalachian South; Lash, Molly; Sutphin, Michael; Sutphin, Michael
- Oral History with Jo Ann Underwood, November 4, 2014, 2014-11-04, Ms2015-007_VTLGBTQ_UnderwoodJoAnn; 01:14:25; The original audio file was recorded as an MP3, duration 01:16:31. Small sections throughout the access file were edited out for clarity, reducing the duration to 01:14:25.
  Jo Ann (Murphy) Underwood pioneered tolerance of sexual minorities on the Virginia Tech campus. She and her family came to Blacksburg in the mid-1970s. She worked as a registered nurse at Virginia Tech’s Student Health Services and was appointed the university’s first health educator in January 1979. A strong advocate for women’s issues, safe sex, birth control, and tolerance of sexual minorities, she started the peer education program at Virginia Tech in the mid-1980s. Her columns in the Collegiate Times helped educate students about various health issues. She served as an advisor to the gay students’ group, Lambda Horizon. At one time she was known as the “Condom Queen of Virginia Tech” because of her diligence in working to prevent sexually transmitted disease. In June 2014, she was named Ally of the Year at the sixth annual Lavender Ceremony for lesbian, gay, bisexual and transgender graduates and their allies. After the ceremony, it was announced that the award would henceforth be called the Underwood Ally of the Year Award.
  The interview explores Jo Ann Underwood’s work as health educator at Virginia Tech and her involvement with the gay students’ group, Lambda Horizon. Underwood’s family background and her husband Richard’s civil rights work in the Together magazine are also discussed. The interview was conducted at Jo Ann Underwood’s residence in Blacksburg, VA. Damon Kinmond was the interviewer and Whitney Wright was the technical assistant.
  Oral History with Jo Ann Underwood, November 4, 2014.
  Sexual minorities; University History; Kinmond, Damon; Underwood, Jo Ann; Underwood, Jo Ann
- Oral History with Mark Weber, March 26, 2015, 2015-03-26, Ms2015-007_VTLGBTQ_WeberMark; 02:33:46
  Mark Alan Weber, class of 1987, was born and raised in Northern Virginia. When he was a student at Virginia Tech, he served first as secretary and then as president of the gay student group, Lambda Horizon. He earned a bachelor’s of business marketing at Virginia Tech and an M.B.A. in marketing from George Washington University. He is Director of Communications, Substance Abuse and Mental Health Services Administration, which is an agency within the U.S. Department of Health and Human Services.
  The interview tells about the beginning of Lambda Horizon on the Virginia Tech campus in the 1980s, the organization’s struggle to be treated equitably, and the work that the organization did. Weber discusses forming the AIDS Education Committee and organizing an AIDS Education Forum at Virginia Tech on March 3, 1986. Virginia Tech along with University of California Berkeley were recognized by the American College Health Association (ACHA) for their students’ AIDS education efforts, and the students were invited to present their work at the ACHA annual meeting in New Orleans. The interview also addresses issues around coming out to one’s family. The interview was conducted at InnovationSpace on the Virginia Tech campus. Tamara Kennelly was the interviewer.
  Oral History with Mark Weber, March 26, 2015.
  University History; Sexual minorities; Weber, Mark A.; Weber, Mark A.; Kennelly, Tamara
- Oral History with John Gray Williams, October 28, 2014, 2014-10-28, Ms2015-007_VTLGBTQ_WilliamsJohnGray; 01:48:51
  John Gray Williams is a Career Advisor in Career Services at Virginia Tech. From 2005 to 2008 he also attended Virginia Tech as an undergraduate student in the Bachelor of Arts in Public and Urban Affairs program. He has been active in LGBTQ activism since he first came to Virginia Tech, working on events such as the Freedom to Marry Day, Gay? Fine by Me Rally, and the LGBTA Relay for Life. As a member of the faculty, he has organized a yearly LGBTQ networking reception and has served as a trainer for the SafeZone program. In his role in Career Services, he is a passionate social justice advocate and works to help members of marginalized populations identify discrimination concerns in the job market.
  The interview was conducted on October 28, 2014 at John Gray Williams’s home in Blacksburg, VA. The interviewer was Whitney Wright and she was assisted by Damon Kinmond. There was limited time for the interview and there are moments within the interview where discussion of the time and Williams’s evening plans can be heard. The interview lasts almost two hours. It begins with a description of Williams’s family and their social dynamics and proceeds into his early experience and understanding of his sexuality and his motivations for choosing to be closeted. The interview then moves into his time at Tidewater Community College where he was first able to research homosexuality and the history of the LGBTQ civil rights movement. He then discusses his decision to transfer to Virginia Tech to pursue a career in Landscape Architecture and his decision to come out to his family. A significant portion of the interview is concerned with his involvement with the LGBTA at Virginia Tech and the variety of protests and events he participated in while completing his undergraduate degree. Then, he discusses his decision to attend the University of Delaware to pursue student affairs while remaining close enough to Blacksburg to maintain a relationship with a student at Virginia Tech. He then describes his return to Virginia Tech as a faculty member and the work he has done to support the LGBTQ community and other marginalized populations since returning. Finally, he discusses broader issues affecting the LGBTQ community beyond the fight for marriage equality.
  Interview
  Oral History with John Gray Williams, October 28, 2014.
  University History; Sexual minorities; Williams, John Gray; Wright, Whitney; Williams, John Gray